Department of Earth and Ocean Sciences Records UA159
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Earth and Ocean Sciences Records
1850 -- 2012
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Geology
Department of Earth and Ocean Studies
School of Arts and Sciences
UA159
20.6 Linear Feet 13 boxes and 1 oversize folder
8 Artifact(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Equipment and instruments and Unprocessed accessions.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains articles; books and booklets; building plans; correspondence; course catalogs and course packets; equipment and instruments; notes; photographs; and serials. The materials document the activities of the Department of Geology and the Department of Earth and Ocean Studies. Prominent individuals include Robert L. Nichols, a noted explorer, geologist, and Tufts University faculty member.
Biographical / Historical
The Department of Geology first appeared in the Catalogue of Tufts College for the 1892-1893 academic year. By the 1893-1894 academic year, the Department of Geology articulates a list of courses that comprise its curriculum. Professor Marshall is listed as being the head of the Department. For the 1902-1903 academic year, the Department of Geology articulated the following philosophy and mission statement, "The subjects offered in the department of Geology have a twofold object: to give an outline of the structure and history of the earth; and to give a training in the methods of observational science".
Professor Alfred Church Lane, a leading scholar and a long-serving chairman of the Department of Geology resigned during the 1935-1936 academic year over his refusal to sign the "loyalty oath" which the state of Massachusetts had recently made a precondition for individuals teaching in its schools. The state law which stipulated the signing of the "loyalty oath" as a precondition for teaching in Massachusetts schools called on teachers to "support the Constitution of the United States and the Constitution of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts".
The Department of Geology began offering a Master of Arts degree for the 1939-1940 academic year. It concluded this degree program after the 1970-1971 academic year.
In 2012, the name of the department was changed to the Department of Earth and Ocean Sciences.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs; Curriculum and Instruction -- Teaching Material
- Equipment and Instruments, 1900 -- 1950; UA159.001; 2.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains equipment, such as microscopes, used by the Department of Geology staff and students.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as found.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Gurley survey scope, 1900 -- 1950; UA159.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Housed in leather case with carrying strap.
  - Gurley survey scope, 1900 -- 1950; UA159.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Gurley survey scope, 1900 -- 1950; UA159.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Gurley survey scope, 1900 -- 1950; UA159.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Leitz microscope, 1911; UA159.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
    Housed in wooden case with key in lock; repaired in the 1940s.
  - Leitz microscope, 1911; UA159.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
    Housed in wooden case with key in lock.
  - Leitz binocular microscope, 1911 -- 1912; UA159.001.007.00001 (Box 7)
    Purchased by Alfred C. Lane in 1911 or 1912; housed in wooden case.
- Additional accessions, UA159.002
  - Specimen Collection Inventories, 1860 -- 1960; UA159-002 (Box data_value_missing_a81c4d39cf28944c4f7b53c8559ca9ee, Box 1)
  - Books, pamphlets and manuals, including Nichols materials, 1860 -- 1950; UA159-003 (Box data_value_missing_4cae6b4794ea6a1094053b36043aca8e, Box 2)
  - Chemical analysis set and microscope, 1860 -- 1900; UA159-004 (Box data_value_missing_4cae6b4794ea6a1094053b36043aca8e, Box 3)
  - Thin sections and samples, 1860 -- 1950; UA159-005 (Box data_value_missing_be1fefd1305e05ba77b491f9503152e2, Box 4)
  - Surveying equipment, 1900 -- 1950; UA159-006 (Box data_value_missing_59709096e477a7f12bc4198a0efac809, Box 5)
  - Microscope, glass slides, samples, 1860 -- 1950; UA159-007 (Box data_value_missing_59709096e477a7f12bc4198a0efac809, Box 6)
  - Pencil drawing by John P. Marshall, 1860 -- 1900; UA159-008; Marshall, John P. (Box data_value_missing_be1fefd1305e05ba77b491f9503152e2, Box 7)
  - Course descriptions, newsletters, and office files, 1970 -- 2012; UA159-009 (Box 2, Box 8)
    75 years from date of creation.
  - Plates lab manual, 1950 -- 2000; UA159-010 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 2)
  - Chemistry set, 1850 -- 1950; UA159-011 (Box Shared 8)
  - Alfred C. Lane, James D. Hume, and Robert L. Nichols reprints and teaching manuals, 1950 -- 1990; UA159-012; Lane, Alfred Church; Hume, Dr. James D.; Nichols, Robert L., 1904-1958 (Box data_value_missing_3255bb1be43da67ce3ee81809f32ceba, Box 9)
  - Robert L. Nichols reprints and slides, 1950 -- 1990; UA159-013; Nichols, Robert L., 1904-1958 (Box data_value_missing_3255bb1be43da67ce3ee81809f32ceba, Box 10)
  - Robert L. Nichols slides, 1950 -- 1990; UA159-015; Nichols, Robert L., 1904-1958 (Box data_value_missing_3255bb1be43da67ce3ee81809f32ceba, Box 11)